Guide to the Duke Family Papers, 1885-1992 (bulk 1892-1927)
Duke University. University Archives
Duke Family papers 1885-1992 (bulk 1892-1927)
Duke University. University Archives
Duke family
9.0 linear feet Extent: approx. 3,000 Items
James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke (1856-1925) was known for his business acumen, especially in national and international tobacco industries and hydroelectric power. He was married twice, first to Lillian McCredy, who he divorced in 1906 and then Nanaline Holt Inman, who was his spouse from 1907 until his death in 1925. This collection primarily documents James B. Duke's business and personal activities. Materials include business and personal correspondence, invoices and receipts for both business and personal purchases, financial and legal reports, the last will and testaments of both James B. and Nanaline Duke, and materials documenting the divorce proceedings of J.B. and Lillian McCredy Duke. Miscellaneous records include a booklet tracing the Duke family geneaology.
uadukefamilypapers
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use. Due to the fragility of the architectural records, The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Duke Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a donation from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in June 2009.
Biographical Note
James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke (1856-1925) was known for his business acumen, especially in national and international tobacco industries and hydroelectric power. He was married twice, first to Lillian McCredy, whom he divorced in 1906 and then Nanaline Holt Inman, who was his spouse from 1907 until his death in 1925.
Collection Overview
The Duke Family Papers (formerly DKFM) are part of the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation Historical Archives which were donated to the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library by the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The collection spans the years 1885 to 1992, although the bulk of the material dates from the 1890s to the mid-1920s. The collection is arranged into six series: Correspondence, Financial Records, Legal Records, Miscellaneous Records, the Divorce Proceedings of James B. Duke and Lillian McCredy Duke, and Architectural Records. The collection primarily documents James B. Duke's business and personal activities. The correspondence is a combination of business and personal letters, with many of the personal letters related to his philanthropy, such as requests from individuals for financial aid and other forms of assistance or favors, such as making investments and employment. Financial records include invoices and receipts for his businesses such as the British American Tobacco Company and the Raritan Power Co., and purchases for his Fifth Avenue mansion in New York City, Duke Farms in New Jersey, and other personal belongings such as furniture, clothing, and jewelry. The collection also documents the administration of the Estate of James B. Duke, including legal proceedings stemming from claims made against the estate after the will of James B. Duke had been executed. A quarter of the collection focuses on the divorce of J.B. Duke and his first wife Lillian, including statements and affidavits of witnesses involved in the divorce proceedings.Miscellaneous records include a booklet tracing the Duke family geneaology and the Duke Name Project including incomplete names of Duke family members. The architectural records include one drawing for J.B. Duke's home in Charlotte, North Carolina. The remaining architectural records document the residence of Walker P. Inman. The materials in this collection are arranged loosely in chronological order.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
American Tobacco Company -- History; Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925; Duke, Lillian McCredy; Duke, Nanaline Holt Inman; Duke Endowment; Duke family; Tobacco Industry -- North Carolina
Related Material
James B. Duke and Lillian McCredy Duke Divorce Papers, 1904-1906
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Buchanan Duke Papers, 1777-1990
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Endowment Reference Collection, 1964-ongoing
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Washington Duke Papers, 1764-1987
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1892-1920
  This series contains a mixture of business and personal correspondence. Business correspondence topics include American Tobacco Co., daily transactions, solicitations for donations, and other business ventures. Personal correspondence includes matters related to Duke Farms and personal letters from immediate and distant family members. Correspondence is generally to/from J.B. Duke, but includes correspondence to and from immediate family members such as Nanaline Duke (Mrs. J.B.), Benjamin Duke, Angier Biddle Duke, and Mary Duke.
  - Correspondence relating to J.B. Duke’s purchases of automobiles. 1906, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence sent to J.B. Duke from Cary H. Whitaker, Pastor, The Methodist Protestant Church, Graham, N.C. In this letter, Pastor Whitaker requests financial aid from Mr. Duke for the repair of the Church building. He also informs him that one of Washington Duke’s wives is buried in the Church cemetery. J.B.Duke responds by sending a $25 donation. November 2–6, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence relating to various topics including J.B. Duke’s projects. Includes work by Trumbauer at 1 E. 78th St. 1912–1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence sent to J.B. Duke from Ethel Arrington requesting financial aid from Mr. Duke. Duke responds by sending a $20 donation. November 9–11, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to Benjamin Duke regarding a variety of matters including donation requests and thank yous for donations. 1914–1915 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence sent to J.B. Duke from nephew Buchanan Duke. January 15, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence between Benjamin Duke and J.B. Duke. 1892–1899 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence relating to a variety of matters concerning J.B. Duke, solicitations of companies, speeding warnings from N.J. to J.B. Duke, and invitations to social events. 1894, 1905–1908, 1914–1915 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and other materials relating to operations and business matters of the American Tobacco Co. 1896–1904 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and other materials relating to operations and business matters of the American Tobacco Co. 1897–1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence relating to J.B. Duke’s stock subscriptions to Virginia-Carolina Chemical Company, Richmond, VA. File includes materials relating to lawsuit against company. Includes balance sheets. 1897–1912 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence and other materials relating to operations and business matters of the American Tobacco Co. and British American Tobacco Co. 1900–1904 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and related materials concerning J.B. Duke’s business matters. Includes purchase of statues for Duke Farms and greenhouses. 1901–1913 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, business, relating to J.B. Duke’s daily activities, transactions, and relationships. 1903–1911 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and related materials concerning a variety of business and personal matters. Includes telegram to Miss Duke from “Daddy,” investments, and insurance. Includes letters to/from N. Duke and letters from Famous Players Film Co. 1905–1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence relating to J.B. Duke covering a variety of topics including donation requests, securities, sale of house at 1009 5th Ave., Raritan Water Co., etc. 1907–1916 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence relating to Mary Duke’s wedding at Duke Farms on June 16, 1915, legal suit, May Inman Gray v. Harriett F. Brandon et al., and other matters. 1908–1915 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, business, relating to J.B. Duke’s daily activities, transactions, and relationships. 1912 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, business, relating to J.B. Duke’s daily activities, transactions, and relationships. 1913 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Personal correspondence from various Duke family members, 1912-1915 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, business, relating to J.B. Duke’s daily activities, transactions, and relationships. 1914 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence relating to a variety of matters including quarterly dividends, notices from the Catawba Power Company, curtains in the NY house, notice to stockholders of the Chester Power Company, and other business matters. 1914 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, business, relating to J.B. Duke’s daily activities, transactions, and relationships. 1915 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, business, relating to J.B. Duke’s daily activities, transactions, and relationships. 1915–1916 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letter inviting Nanaline Duke to serve on the Board of Trustees of The Society of the New York Hospital. December 22, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Financial Records, 1892-1962
  This series contains both personal and business financial records. Personal financial records include invoices and receipts for jewelry purchased by Nanaline Duke, home furnishings, art, and interior design records for the Duke's Fifth Avenue mansion,and clothes and toys for daughter Doris. Business financial records consist of invoices, receipts, and related materials from J.B. Duke's business affairs, including receipts for purchases made by the British American Tobacco Co., Ltd. Also in the series are journals and ledgers for the Southern Investment Co. of Canada Limited and the wages of employees, office and miscellaneous salaries from 1919–1950.
  - Receipts relating to a variety of purchases including some personal expenses (jewelry repairs, doctors), Raritan Water Power Co. 1892, 1903–1915 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Invoices from Fifth Avenue Auction Room. 1901 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Invoices and receipts for purchases from various dealers. 1901–1914 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Invoices of jewelry purchases made by Mr. and Mrs. J.B. Duke from Tiffany & Co. 1902-1911 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Invoices for purchases made by J.B. Duke. 1902–1912 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Invoices and receipts for purchases from R.J. Horner & Co. 1905–1907 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Invoices and receipts for purchases from Gilman Collamore & Co. 1906–1911 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Invoice for a Louis XVI panel from E. Spencer Hall & Co. 1908 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Invoices and receipts for purchases made from Elsie de Wolfe. 1908–1909 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Invoices and receipts for purchases made from A. Miller. 1908–1911 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Invoices for furniture purchased by Mrs. J.B. Duke at E. Dreyfus in N.Y.C. File includes other invoices for furniture & furnishing purchases made by Nanaline Duke. 1908–1913 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Estimate for interior design services for Mrs. J.B. Duke at 1009 Fifth Avenue. 1909 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Invoices and receipts for purchases made from Rowatt & Lyon, Ltd. 1910 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Receipt for shipping of grandfather clock from England to U.S.A. for J.B. Duke. 1910 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Receipts - lunch orders for J.B. Duke, 1910-1911 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Invoices and receipts for purchases made from M. Knoedler & Co. 1910–1912 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Invoices and receipts for a variety of services including baby clothes and doctor’s bills for Doris Duke, car repairs, golf course, and other business transactions. 1911–1914 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Invoice for voyage aboard the Lusitania to London from New York for Mr. and Mrs. J.B. Duke, Infant, Maid, Nurse, Mrs. Florine Holt, and Miss Gertrude Nevins for October 4, 1913. Includes invoice for voyage aboard S.S. Olympic for Charles F. Meier on May 3, 1913. April 21–22, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Account receipts for transactions from accounts held by Florine Holt and Nanaline Duke with the Farmers’ Loan and Trust Co. 1913 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Invoices for clothing items for J.B. Duke and Doris Duke. Includes invoices for toys purchased for Doris Duke. Also includes an invoice for services rendered by a wet nurse from Schott’s Wet Nurse Agency. 1913–1915 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Estimate of George Weston, deceased, worth and related materials. George Weston worked at 1 E. 78th St. for Nanaline Duke. 1932 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Nanaline Duke and Doris Duke’s N.Y. State Unemployment Insurance Fund Returns. 1951–1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Income tax returns for J.B. Duke. April 10, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Invoices, receipts, and related materials concerning J.B. Duke’s business affairs. 1903–1904 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Invoices and statements for purchases made by J.B. Duke and the Raritan Power Co. Includes insurance policies for RWPC. 1904–1913 (1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Invoices and statements for purchases made by J.B. Duke and the Raritan Power Co. Includes insurance policies for RWPC. 1904–1913 (2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Invoices, receipts, and related materials concerning J.B. Duke’s business affairs. 1905 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Invoices, receipts, and related materials concerning J.B. Duke’s business affairs. 1906 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Business related records including shares of stock and meeting notices, 1906-1916 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Invoices, receipts, and related materials concerning J.B. Duke’s business affairs. 1907 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Invoices, receipts, and related materials concerning J.B. Duke’s business affairs. 1908 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Invoices, receipts, and related materials concerning J.B. Duke’s business affairs. 1909 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Invoices, receipts, and related materials concerning J.B. Duke’s business affairs. 1910 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Receipts for purchases made by the British American Tobacco Co., Ltd. 1910 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Invoices, receipts, and related materials concerning J.B. Duke’s business affairs. 1911 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Invoices, receipts, and related materials concerning J.B. Duke’s business affairs. 1912 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Invoices, receipts, and related materials concerning J.B. Duke’s business affairs. 1913–1917 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Southern Investment Co. of Canada Limited, Ledger. 1913–1914 (Box 5)
  - Southern Investment Co. of Canada Limited, Journal. 1913–1916 (Box 6)
  - Southern Investment Co. of Canada Limited, Cashbook, Vouchers, and Checks. 1913–1916 (Box 7)
  - Wages of Employees, Office and Miscellaneous Salaries. October 1919–1950 (Box 8)
- Legal Records, 1885-1955
  Materials contained in this series relate to both personal and business matters. Personal records include insurance policies and the last will and testaments of both J.B. Duke and Nanaline Duke. Business records include a complaint filed by Richard H. Wright against James B. Duke, Benjamin N. Duke, Brodie L. Duke, and George W. Watts regarding the sale of the W. Duke, Sons & Co.
  - Insurance policies for automobiles owned by J.B. Duke. 1908–1912 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Lease, J.B. Duke and Olney B. Mairs for Duke’s rental of 1009 Fifth Ave. September 23, 1914 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Insurance policy from Fireman’s Fund to J.B. Duke for robes, blankets, driving and livery garments, and other clothing contained at Nos. 73–75 E. 89th St., Borough of Manhattan, City of N.Y. November 4, 1915 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Indenture and Deed of Trust of Personalty establishing The Duke Endowment. Also, includes addition of thereto by Will of J.B. Duke. 1924–1925 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Last Will and Testament of J.B. Duke (1924) and Codicil (1925). 1924–1925 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Explanation and breakdown of J.B. Duke’s Will and the four Trusts it set up as written by W.R. Perkins. October 26, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Receipt for Legacy and Refunding Bond “In the Matter of the Estate of J.B. Duke, Deceased.” 1926 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - “Determination by the Executors of J.B. Duke, Deceased, of those Entitled to Participate in the Distribution to be Made Under Item VI of the Last Will and Testament of Said Descendant and of the Amounts they are, Respectively, Entitled to Receive.” October 5, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Petition of First Accounting "In the Matter of the Estate of James B. Duke, Deceased." Somerset County Orphans’ Court. 1927 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Appraisal, household furniture and furnishings, at J.B. Duke’s home in Myers Park, Charlotte, N.C. Home also called Lynnewood. 1927 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Order allowing Final Account “In the Matter of the Estate of James B. Duke.” June 15, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Last Will and Testament of Nanaline H. Duke. June 3, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Complaint filed by Richard H. Wright against James B. Duke, Benjamin N. Duke, Brodie L. Duke, and George W. Watts regarding the sale of the W. Duke, Sons & Co. 1885 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Legal brief for “The United States of America against The American Tobacco Company and others.” November 7, 1908 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Proxy authorizing Thomas J. Maloney, William B. Rhett, and Thomas S. Fuller to vote as Nanaline H. Duke’s Proxy at the annual P. Lorillard Company stockholders meeting. 1915 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Copies of legal appraisal in the Estate of James B. Duke, deceased, 1925 Dec, 1926 Jan (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Miscellaneous Records, 1893-1977
  This small series consists of a variety of Duke family related records including a booklet tracing the Duke family geneaology and two logbooks for "Yacht Doris".
  - Report, “Duke’s Four Homes: Black Architect Designs Buildings at Duke University.” Written by Archival Consultant, Inc. 1989 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Report of the Trustees of The Mary Duke Biddle Foundation. 1992 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Booklet tracing the Duke family genealogy. c. 1920s (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Poem eulogizing Angier Buchanan Duke by Plato Tracy Durham, "Aue Atque Vale, Frater! To Angier Buchanan Duke." September 1923 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Duke Name Project listing incomplete names of Duke family members. c. 1960s (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Card from flowers sent to Miss Duke for Nanaline H. Duke’s funeral. 1961 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings on the death of James B. Duke from The World, The News and Observer, and "... Daily News." October 18–28, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Logbook, "Yacht Doris." October 1927–April 1928 (Box 10)
  - Logbook, "Yacht Doris." April 1928–May 1928 (Box 10)
  - Family crest for Edward Duke, circa 1730s (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence sent to J.B. Duke relating to various topics including tobacco and donations, 1893-1913 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Photograph of unknown individual included in "Appraisal of the furnishings of the residence of J.B. Duke, 1 East 78th Street, New York City", 1922 Feb 4 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Invoices of art and furnishings, jewelry purchased. Includes inventories of several estates and a letter to Walker Inman, 1928-1944, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Program, Duke University Founders' Day Observing The One Hundredth Anniversary of the Birth of James Buchanan Duke, 1956 Dec 11 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Civil Action against the Trust Indenture by J.B. Duke, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Christmas card from Nanaline Duke to Mary Duke Biddle, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Divorce Proceedings, James B. Duke v. Lillian Duke, 1892-1907
  This series contains a variety of documents leading up to, during and after the divorce of J.B. Duke and his first wife Lillian. Documents include detective reports recording the activities of Mrs. Duke, statements and affidavits of witnesses involved in the divorce proceedings, cables (written in code) sent and received to and from J.B. Duke, most likely between him and detectives, and petitions, opinions, and legal notices relating to the divorce.
  - Cables and keys to coded cables to and from J.B. Duke, most likely between himself and detectives. Detectives’ correspondence with J.B. Duke about Mrs. Duke’s activities while J.B. Duke was in London. 1905 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Reports of activities of Mr. and Mrs. J.B. Duke and Mary Smith affadavit, 1905 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Cables sent and received by W.M. Fuller, J. Parker, and A.H. Burroughs. Some cables written in code. 1905 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Cables sent and received by J.B. Duke (to and from people other than Mrs. Duke). 1905–1906 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to legal work by J.B. Duke’s lawyers for his divorce case. 1905–1906 (1 of 2) (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to legal work by J.B. Duke’s lawyers for his divorce case. 1905–1906 (2 of 2) (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Materials, including cables to and from J.B. Duke and Lillian McCredy between one another, and testimony from a witness in the Lillian McCredy v. William McCredy divorce proceeding. 1892, 1905 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Court of Common Pleas, N.Y., Lillian McCredy v. William McCredy. January 14, 1893 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Legal Brief For Respondent, J.B. Duke, for the Court of Errors and Appeals. 1905 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Legal notices requesting the appearance of witnesses in the J.B. Duke v. Lillian Duke divorce proceedings. 1905 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Petitions of J.B. Duke, Lillian Duke, Frank T. Huntoon and others related to divorce proceedings. 1905 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Selection of legal notices, petitions, orders, and answers relating to the J.B. Duke v. Lillian Duke divorce in Chancery of N.J. 1905 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Statement of J.B. Duke as to Christmas presents, gifts, etc. made by him on various occasions. 1905–1906 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Statements and affidavits of witnesses involved in the J.B. Duke v. Lillian Duke divorce proceedings. 1905–1906 (1 of 8) (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Statements and affidavits of witnesses involved in the J.B. Duke v. Lillian Duke divorce proceedings. 1905–1906 (2 of 8) (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Statements and affidavits of witnesses involved in the J.B. Duke v. Lillian Duke divorce proceedings. 1905–1906 (3 of 8) (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Statements and affidavits of witnesses involved in the J.B. Duke v. Lillian Duke divorce proceedings. 1905–1906 (4 of 8) (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Statements and affidavits of witnesses involved in the J.B. Duke v. Lillian Duke divorce proceedings. 1905–1906 (5 of 8) (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Statements and affidavits of witnesses involved in the J.B. Duke v. Lillian Duke divorce proceedings. 1905–1906 (6 of 8) (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Statements and affidavits of witnesses involved in the J.B. Duke v. Lillian Duke divorce proceedings. 1905–1906 (7 of 8) (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Statements and affidavits of witnesses involved in the J.B. Duke v. Lillian Duke divorce proceedings. 1905–1906 (8 of 8) (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Statements of Duke servants, Mary Fahey, Ingred Anderson, and Ellie Sutlon for divorce proceedings. 1905–1906 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Testimonies of detectives hired to observe and record Mrs. Duke’s activities. 1905–1906 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Application of J.B. Duke for subpoenas and subpoenas to specific witnesses. 1906 (Box 13, Folder 3)